Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin
N/A
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry Manuscripts
Harry Ransom Center Harry Ransom Center The University of Texas at Austin P.O. Drawer 7219 Austin, Texas 78713-7219
This catalog was created from the finding aid created by the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin, and obtained by the Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers are held at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center.
Restrictions on Original Materials:
Please consult with the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin.
Scope and Content
Handwritten manuscripts, fragments, notes, proofs, galleys, clippings, monographs, correspondence, drawings, photographs, and memorabilia document the life and work of Walt Whitman and include information about Whitman created and collected by several of his early admirers and devotees. The collection is organized into four series: I. Works, 1846-1913, nd (2 boxes), II. Correspondence, 1863-1892, nd (1 box), III. Works and Correspondence by Others, 1863-1956, nd (3 boxes), and IV. Images and Checks, 1875-1887, nd (1 folder)
The earliest dated material consists of tearsheets of "The Tomb-Blossoms," published in 1846 in The United States Magazine and Democratic. The bulk of the materials dated after Whitman's death in 1892 originated with Whitman's friend and biographer, Horace Traubel; Whitman Society President Gustave Percival Wiksell; Whitman scholars Richard M. Bucke and Milton Hindus; and William Douglas O'Connor. In addition to Whitman's original manuscripts, a draft fragment in the hand of Alfred, Lord Tennyson, "VIII | O subtle, various world," is bound with correspondence between Whitman and Tennyson and manuscript material for Leaves of Grass "Sands at Seventy: To Get the Final Lilt of Songs."
Many of the manuscripts and letters are in fragile condition and access to individual items may be limited while they undergo conservation treatment. All Whitman items are handwritten unless otherwise indicated. Additional Whitman material is located in the Ransom Center's vertical files, art collection, photography collection, and personal effects.
Only those items deemed poetry and/or prose manuscripts are described in this catalog.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Series Description and Item List
- Works, 1846-1913 and undated
  Works are arranged alphabetically by title or first line. Many of the poems included in Leaves of Grass are listed alphabetically under that title. The bulk of the materials are handwritten manuscripts, fragments, and notes. Six unidentified fragments may include writing by someone other than Whitman, possibly Horace Traubel.
  Other materials in the series include one-page printed proofs of individual poems, clippings of published articles, and galley proofs. Of note is an 1876 edition of Leaves of Grass in paper wrappers with numerous handwritten additions and corrections by Whitman. Other major works represented include Democratic Vistas, O Captain My Captain, Specimen Days & Collect, and Two Rivulets.
  Two headings, "Works I" and "Miscellaneous I," list individual works bound or grouped together previous to their acquisition by the Ransom Center. These works have been kept together physically, but the titles of individual works are listed in the appropriate alphabetical sequence in the folder list. "Miscellaneous I" also contains several items about Whitman, similar to materials found in "Series III: Works and Correspondence by Others."
  - A Riddle Song, 1880; tex.00027; xxx.00277; poetry prose 4 leaves handwritten; printed (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Manuscript and corrected proof of A Riddle Song, a poem which first appeared in the Tarrytown Sunnyside Press on 3 April 1880. It was reprinted in Forney’s Progress (Philadelphia) 2 ( 17 April 1880 ): 508, and then included in the 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass. Also included is a cover note that describes the contents and declares that Whitman presented them to Richard Bucke on 26 May 1880.
  - A Riddle Song, 1880; tex.00097; xxx.00277; poetry 1 leaf newspaper clipping (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Clipping of the poem A Riddle Song probably from the Camden Daily Post, as is suggested by writing on the verso. The reference to the Tarrytown Sunnyside Press in the bottom right corner serves to credit the newspaper in which Whitman's poem first appeared.
  - Lecture by Walt Whitman on Abraham Lincoln, 1886; tex.00328; xxx.00531; prose about 16 leaves newspaper clipping (Bound bv5)
    Notes for the lecture on the death of Abraham Lincoln that Whitman delivered in Philadelphia on April 15, 1886. The notes consist of clippings from earlier printings of the lecture with a few handwritten revisions. The lecture was first published as Death of Lincoln in the New York Sun on February 12, 1876. A revised version appeared as A Poet on the Platform in the New York Daily Tribune on April 15, 1879. In Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ) it was titled Death of Abraham Lincoln. Lecture deliver'd in New York, April 14, 1879—in Philadelphia, '80—in Boston, '81. The notes are mounted in a bound volume along with the letter that Whitman sent with them to Thomas Donaldson, a note written by Donaldson, an engraving of Whitman, and a ticket to a performance of the lecture on April 14, 1887.
  - [Advance shapes like his shape], about 1855; tex.00028; xxx.00689; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Manuscript of approximately eight lines, lightly revised, celebrating the legendary Egyptian ruler Sesostris. No relationship is known between this manuscript and Whitman's published work. Walt Whitman's description may be derived from his reading of Sir John Gardiner Wilkinson's Manners and Customs of the Ancient Egyptians (1836-1840).
  - After all, not to create only, about 1871; tex.00069; xxx.00117; poetry 29 leaves handwritten (Folder bv1)
    Draft of the poem After all, Not to Create Only, written for the opening of the fortieth Annual Exhibition of the American Institute in 1871 and published on 7 September 1871 in both the New York Commercial Advertiser and the New York Evening Post. It was reprinted in several newspapers and as a pamphlet, After All, Not to Create Only (1871); as "Song of the Exposition" in Two Rivulets (1876); and with some revisions in Leaves of Grass (1881–82). Sheets from the pamphlet were included in some copies of the 1871 Leaves of Grass. A note at the top of the manuscript, written by Whitman's friend William Sloane Kennedy, indicates that it was used as printer's copy for the pamphlet publication.
  - [All tends to the soul], about 1860; tex.00059; xxx.00690; xxx.00047; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Draft of a poem about the relationship of the soul to the material world. This manuscript contributed to the poem Proto-Leaf, which was first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass and eventually titled Starting from Paumanok.
  - [Americans are charged with disproportionate brag and], 1819-1872; tex.00003; xxx.00501; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1)
    A paragraph, heavily revised, expressing the opinion that the United States is the culmination of human development. A note at the bottom of the sheet, "As a Strong Bird," may refer to the poem As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free, which was first published in the New York Herald on 26 June 1872. Extracts from this poem also appeared in the Washington Evening Star on the same date, within a larger article on the commencement exercises at Dartmouth College. It more likely, however, refers to the slender volume in which the poem was published later that year, As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free. And Other Poems. This manuscript is probably part of an early draft of the preface for that volume. The poem As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free was subsequently included in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ). After adding a new opening stanza and making additional revisions, Whitman incorporated the poem into Leaves of Grass (1881–82) under the new title Thou Mother with Thy Equal Brood. The preface was reprinted, with minor changes, as Preface, 1872, to 'As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free' in the 1892 volume Comple Prose Works.
  - Among the many aspects of thought… It is not this business of voting… [Among the many] [It is not this], about 1881; tex.00004; xxx.00269; xxx.00505; xxx.00524; poetry prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1, Folder 5)
    On one side of the leaves, Whitman explores the idea that life, with its petty concerns, is "an exercise, a training & development" for an afterlife. A note at the top possibly indicates that the poet considered developing this thought in conjunction with From Noon to Starry Night, a cluster that first appeared in the 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass. Edward F. Grier suggests, alternatively, that the writing is connected with Specimen Days ( 1882–83 ), "which is full of references to stars" (Walt Whitman, Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts, Edward F. Grier, ed. [New York: New York University Press, 1984], 6:2106). The writing on the reverse sides of the leaves explores the ideal roles of authors and the general public in shaping government and legislation. These notes are possibly related to Democratic Vistas, in which Whitman discusses the role of what he calls here the literary class in connection to democracy, as well as issues of voting and women's rights. The two leaves are housed and described separately at the repository.
  - Song of Myself [And to me each minute of the night], before 1855; tex.00057; xxx.00048; xxx.00266; xxx.00526; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    About ten draft lines of the opening poem of the 1855 Leaves of Grass, ultimately titled Song of Myself. This manuscript passage is made up of versions of lines that appeared in the first published version of the poem, as well as in the 1855 preface. Various lines from this one passage appear in widely scattered places: in the final version of Song of Myself, they appear in sections 5, 13, 16, 31, 36, and 43, while others appear in the poem eventually entitled To Think of Time and in the pre-1855 manuscript poem Pictures. The verso shows a tentative arrangement of the poems for the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, with working titles.
  - ['Animals,' says George Eliot], undated; tex.00091; xxx.00691; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Three manuscript leaves and two newspaper clippings pasted to a larger backing sheet. All but one of the scraps presents an aphorism attributable to someone other than Whitman. The other, also aphoristic, is fragmentary but appears to be a draft line of verse. According to Edward F. Grier, the handwriting in the first and third paragraphs is that of the 1850s or 1860s; that of the second one seems to be the looser, more irregular writing of the 1870s.
  - [Armies & navies pass on the surface], probably 1850-1870; tex.00005; xxx.00625; xxx.00626; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This manuscript was probably composed in the 1850s or 1860s. On one side of the leaf are approximately five lines toward a poem about the effects of war that was never published in Whitman's lifetime. On the other side are two sentences or lines, one headed "Locust," and the other headed "Sunflower." The relationship of these notes to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - As at thy Portals also Death, about 1881; tex.00006; xxx.00298; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Draft, with revisions, of As at Thy Portals Also Death, which was first published in the 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass. A second, smaller leaf, was at some point pasted over the lines at the bottom of the first leaf, but it has become separated and is at present stored separately as [To her, the ideal woman].
  - [To her, the ideal woman], about 1881; tex.00048; xxx.00298; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Draft, with revisions, of the final three lines of As at Thy Portals Also Death, which was first published in the 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass.
  - As one by one withdraw the lofty actors, 1885; tex.00007; xxx.00341; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Printer's copy, annotated and lightly corrected, of the poem first published under the title As One by One Withdraw the Lofty Actors in Harper's Weekly, 16 May 1885. The poem was reprinted as Grant in the Critic, 15 August 1885 and revised as Death of General Grant in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
  - Astronomy… [astronomy], 1881 or 1882; tex.00194; xxx.00825; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Two brief notes written on what appears to be a scrap from a small notebook. The note at the top of the scrap furnished an image that Whitman used in Full-Starr'd Nights, first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The other note refers to an article titled A Study of Carlyle, published in the April 1881 issue (vol. 39, pp. 494–609) of Contemporary Review and signed "The Author of 'The Moral Influence of George Eliot.'" The article thus referred to had appeared in the February 1881 issue (vol. 39, pp. 173–185), with the signature "One who Knew Her."
  - A Soul Duet, probably before 1855; tex.00014; xxx.00602; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Heavily revised draft of a poem unpublished in Whitman's lifetime. The regular, rhymed structure and pious theme suggest a date before the first edition of Leaves of Grass in 1855.
  - [become a shroud], about 1855; tex.00030; xxx.00264; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Approximately seven draft lines, lightly revised, of the poem eventually titled The Sleepers, first published in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. The manuscript on the reverse side, tex.00460, contributed to the poem Unnamed Lands, first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass.
  - [off, dim and filmy in their outlines], between 1855 and 1860; tex.00460; xxx.00231; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Prose fragment, showing moderate revision, of approximately 150 words. Phrases and ideas from this manuscript were incorporated in the poem Unnamed Lands, first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. The manuscript on the reverse, tex.00030, was probably written earlier, as it contributed to a poem first published in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass and eventually titled The Sleepers.
  - Branches & sprigs of lilacs, about 1870; tex.00013; xxx.00234; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 2)
    A note expressing Whitman's intentions for the revision of a poem or group of poems, the identity of which is uncertain. A connection to Warble for Lilac-Time, first published in 1870, seems likely, however.
  - Bravo, Paris Exposition!, undated; tex.00082; xxx.00392; poetry 1 leaf proof with handwritten corrections (Bound bv2)
    Bravo, Paris Exposition! was published in Harper's Weekly 33, 28 September 1889. It was reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy (1891) and in Leaves of Grass (1891–1892). According to a letter from Whitman to R. M. Bucke, this poem was also reprinted in the French paper "Le Temps." This proof has been pasted down to a backing sheet, rendering the verso inaccessible.
  - By Emerson's Grave, By Emerson's Grave, 1882; tex.00198; xxx.00921; prose 4 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Three-page printer's copy of the essay By Emerson's Grave, published in the May 6, 1882, issue of the Critic and later reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The envelope in which Whitman sent the manuscript to the paper's editors is also included.
  - [Seems to me I may dare to claim a deep native], about 1888; tex.00206; xxx.00934; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Partial draft of Note at End of Complete Poems and Prose, which was published in Complete Poems & Prose ( 1888 ) and not reprinted during Whitman's lifetime. No image of the manuscript's verso is available.
  - Death of Carlyle, 1881; tex.00210; xxx.00885; prose 7 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Incomplete printer's copy of The Death of Carlyle, which was published in the February 12, 1881, issue of the Critic. It also appeared, under the title The Dead Carlyle, in the Boston Literary World on the same date. It was later reprinted as Death of Thomas Carlyle in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ). The accompanying authentication certificate, signed by Critic editor Jeannette Gilder, mentions that the missing final page of the manuscript bore Whitman's signature.
  - The Conscience - the moral one, The Consciences—the Moral one, about 1888; tex.00208; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 3)
    This manuscript fragment regarding the importance of the spiritual aspect of human consciousness is probably part of a draft of A Lingering Note in Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks. The essay was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ). The leaf has been pasted to a backing sheet, rendering the verso inaccessible.
  - [Do you know what music does] An Essay on the Soul, about 1855; tex.00088; prose poetry 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Approximately seven paragraphs, propounding a set of beliefs about the nature of the human soul. The first paragraph is probably related to a passage in the poem eventually titled A Song For Occupations that explores the nature of musical perception. The sixth paragraph expresses, in brief, ideas that are elaborated in the poem Who Learns My Lesson Complete. As both of these poems appeared in the first edition of Leaves of Grass in 1855, this manuscript was apparently written before that date, while Whitman was exploring various literary forms for the expression of his ideas.
  - Echoes and Supplements, between 1884 and 1892; tex.00117; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Trial title, possibly for a projected sequel to Specimen Days & Collect, written on the reverse of a scrap torn from a mailing label addressed to Whitman. A note in the hand of Horace Traubel identifies the sender as T. W. Rolleston, co-author of the first book-length German translation of Leaves of Grass ( 1889 ).
  - Family member list with birthdays, notes, Here is a list of the immediate family, about 1883; tex.00215; xxx.00949; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    On one side of this leaf is a list of Whitman's family members, which Whitman wrote for inclusion in the introduction to Richard Maurice Bucke's 1883 biography, Walt Whitman. The writing on the reverse side is in both Whitman's and Bucke's hands and has been cancelled. It consists of draft versions of the heading for William Douglas O'Connor's The Good Gray Poet ( 1866 ), which was reprinted in the biography.
  - For Queen Victoria's Birth-Day For Queen Victoria's Birth-Day For Queen Victoria's Birth-Day, about 1891; tex.00020; xxx.00557; poetry prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Lightly revised printer's copy of For Queen Victoria's Birthday, which was published in Good-Bye My Fancy in 1891. In the same folder are an uncorrected proof sheet and an envelope, which is inscribed with a note in Whitman's hand, indicating that he presented them together as a gift to an unknown recipient. No images of the proof sheet are available.
  - For the notes… [for the Notes], about 1888; tex.00221; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This short note refers to a passage in the third edition of Edward FitzGerald's The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám, the Astronomer-Poet of Persia, published in 1872. Whitman quotes stanza 66 of FitzGerald's work in his essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, which was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). He had apparently intended to include, as a footnote to his quotation, the next three stanzas of the Rubáiyát, but these do not appear in the article as it was printed.
  - Halcyon Days, about 1888; tex.00072; xxx.00329; poetry 1 leaf (Box bv2)
    Heavily revised draft, approximately eleven lines, of Halcyon Days, which was first published in the 29 January 1888 issue of the New York Herald. One the reverse is a letter from Fred W. Waggert, dated "4th June 1887."
  - [hear outside the orders given], about 1865; tex.00012; xxx.00188; xxx.00832; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Five partly cropped lines from a draft of the poem A March in the Ranks Hard-Pressed, and the Road Unknown, first published in Drum-Taps in 1865. The manuscript on the reverse side, tex.00461, is perhaps related to the essay The Real War Will Never Get in the Books, published in Specimen Days ( 1882–83 ).
  - [The bivouac does not the voice of], between 1865 and 1883; tex.00461; xxx.00832; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Two lines of verse, with revisions. The relation of these lines to Whitman's published poetry is uncertain, though in concept and imagery they echo a passage from The Real War Will Never Get in the Books, a prose piece that appeared in Specimen Days ( 1882–83 ). There, the poet writes that the war was not a quadrille in a ball-room. The lines on the other side of the leaf, tex.00012, are for the Drum-Taps ( 1865 ) poem A March in the Ranks Hard-Pressed, and the Road Unknown.
  - [waited their due time to clean the rubbish], about 1855; tex.00079; xxx.00269; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    A small scrap with three partial lines of poetry, cancelled by a vertical strike, from a draft of the poem ultimately titled Faces. This was the sixth poem of the first edition of Leaves of Grass in 1855, where it appeared under the title Leaves of Grass. On the reverse is tex.00321, a fragment with no known relation to Whitman's published work.
  - [I cannot guess what the entertainment], about 1855; tex.00321; xxx.00487; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    A small scrap bearing three lines of poetry with no discernible relation to Whitman's published work, though the hand, ink, and paper are consistent with other known pre-1855 manuscripts. The lines on the reverse, tex.00079, contributed to the poem ultimately titled Faces.
  - [Idea of a Poem], undated; tex.00025; xxx.00016; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Notes, approximately forty words, toward a poem of "celebration of the superiority of the night," perhaps related to the poem eventally titled Night on the Prairies, first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass as No. 15 in the Leaves of Grass cluster. This manuscript has been pasted down to a backing sheet and the verso is inaccessible.
  - Idea of New Po[em?], about 1875; tex.00108; xxx.00693; poetry 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Brief note outlining a poem to express modern views of myth, religion, etc. Pasted at the bottom of the leaf is a clipping, taken from an unidentified newspaper, titled "King Ludwig's Latest Whim," which describes plans to move monumental religious statues to a mountain peak overlooking Oberammergau by means of a "street locomotive." The events described in the clipping occurred in 1875. It is unknown what connection, if any, this manuscript bears to published poems, though the "idea" it outlines is one that Whitman treated frequently.